Register of the Poland. Konsulat Generalny (Lille, France) Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Konsulat Generalny (Lille, France) records,
1926-1940
59029
Poland. Konsulat Generalny (Lille, France)
11 manuscript boxes (4.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, dispatches, memoranda, financial records, passports and passport applications, and printed matter, relating to Franco-Polish relations, Polish citizens and consular affairs in France, and conditions in Poland and France during World War II. A digital copy of this entire collection is available at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/40/0/-/.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Also available on microfilm (13 reels).
Digital copy in Poland's National Digital Archive at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/40/0/-/. It was digitized from microfilm by the Polish State Archives.
Historical Note
Polish consulate general in Lille.
Scope and Content Note
History of the records:
The Consulate General in Lille opened in 1921, less than three years after Poland's proclamation of independence. It was located in the Nord-Pas de Calais region, an area with a large concentration of Polish immigrants. That population kept growing with the need of the local economy for unskilled labor and the inability of Poland, though it was experiencing its own industrial revival in the early twenties, to absorb its surplus of labor. During the inter-war period, it is estimated that 600,000 Poles immigrated to Northern France, 150,000 of whom from Germany's Rhein and Westphalia regions alone.
Neighboring countries such as Belgium, Denmark, and Germany had their own sizeable Polish colonies established since the turn of the century, but it was the French government that was most willing to regulate issues arising from the employment of foreigners, thanks in large measure to Poland's strong diplomatic presence in France. (The two countries signed a labor agreement in 1919.)
Indeed, before the outbreak of the Second World War, the Consulate was one of over thirty Polish posts established both in France and in its colonies. This unusually high number reflected the special relations between the two countries and the importance Poland attached to economic and political ties with Paris.
Initially, the work of the Consulate was limited almost exclusively to administrative and social matters, and its records relate mostly to the policies of the Polish Foreign Ministry toward Polish communities abroad. That emphasis changed in the second half of the 1930s, with the increase in international tensions, particularly with the outbreak of the Spanish Civil War. Some of the politically active labor circles among Polish immigrants, especially the communists, showed sympathy for the republican side. There was also evidence of increasing Soviet propaganda activity. Those issues were of great concern to both the French and Polish sides, but there is very little in the collection on Franco-Polish relations.
After the German invasion of June 1940, the Consulate was evacuated and portions of the records were destroyed; what was left went to England, and remains the only surviving record. The Consulate resumed operations after France's liberation in 1944, but that period is not covered in these files.
Classification system:
These records were formerly part of the Polish Foreign Ministry collection, acquired by the Hoover Archives in 1959, and were accessioned in the early 1990s as a separate collection. Its classification system is the same as that of the Ministry, established in the 1930s and consisting of 900 index numbers, 200 of which were left blank, available to be used for additional topics, which is in fact what happened during the war.
Except for the Polish legation to the Czechoslovak government in London, all other legations, embassies, and consulates used that classification system, though of course not all of the 900 possible series are reflected in their records; those of the Consulate General in Lille, for instance, cover only eighty or so of them. Each diplomatic post was assigned a number, in this case series no. 593, entitled "Consulate General in Lille, France," which deals with the Consulate's budgetary and financial affairs.
For a complete listing of the numbers in that classification system, please consult the series list of the register to the "Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych" records.
A microfilm copy of these materials has been deposited in the State Archives of Poland in Warsaw.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
France--Foreign relations--Poland.; Poles--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; Poland.; France.; World War, 1939-1945.; Poland--Foreign relations--France.
Container List
- General. Series list compiled by the Consulate General in Lille, France (Box-folder 1: 1)
- SERIES NO. 2. MINISTRY'S INSTRUCTIONS. Instructions concerning contingency plans for 1940 (Folder 1: 2)
- SERIES NO. 3. POLITICAL REPORTS
  - 1934-1936 (Folder 1: 3)
  - 1938 (Folder 1: 4)
  - 1939 (Folder 1: 5)
- SERIES NO. 14. COLONIAL POLICY, 1936 (Folder 1: 6)
- SERIES NO. 21. FINANCES AND CREDITS, 1936-1938 (Folder 1: 7)
- SERIES NO. 31. LABOR MARKET, 1934-1935. (Folder 1: 8)
  Leforest strikes
- SERIES NO. 32. JOB AVAILABILITY FOR FOREIGNERS, 1938 (Folder 1: 9)
- SERIES NO. 49. POLITICAL RELATIONS WITH POLAND IN GENERAL, 1938-1939 (Folder 1: 10)
- SERIES NO. 50. PROPAGANDA IN SPECIFIC POLITICAL ISSUES
  - 1931 - Stahlheim meeting in Breslau (Folder 1: 11)
  - 1932 - Danzig. (Folder 1: 12)
    Memorandum to High Commissioner of League of Nations
  - 1935-1939 (Folder 1: 13)
- SERIES NO. 82. COMMERCIAL AND CUSTOM AGREEMENTS
  - 1934-1936 (Folder 1: 14)
  - 1937 - Commercial treaty
    - General
      - General (Folder 1: 15)
      - Transcript (Folder 1: 16)
    - International Exposition in Paris (Folder 1: 17)
- SERIES NO. 85. INSURANCE AND LABOR AGREEMENTS
  - General (Folder 1: 18)
  - 1930 (Folder 1: 19)
  - 1932
    - General (Folder 1: 20)
    - Polish workers abroad (Folder 1: 21)
  - 1935. (Folder 1: 22)
    Zestawienie Tekstow Polsko-Francuskich Umow Emigracyjnych: Wedlug Stanu z dnia 1 stycznia 1935 r.
  - 1937-1939 (Folder 1: 23)
- SERIES NO. 153. INTELLECTUAL COOPERATION - Budzynski, Wladyslaw
  - 1927
    - General (Folder 1: 24)
    - Clippings (Folder 1: 25)
  - 1928-1929 (Folder 1: 26)
  - 1933-1934 (Folder 1: 27)
  - 1937-1939 (Folder 1: 28)
- SERIES NO. 193. ACADEMIC YOUTH (Box 2)
  - 1931 (Folder 2: 1)
  - 1932 (Folder 2: 2)
  - 1933 (Folder 2: 3)
  - 1934-1935 (Folder 2: 4)
  - 1936-1937 (Folder 2: 5)
  - 1938-1939 (Folder 2: 6)
- SERIES NO. 206. GUARANTEES OF CONFIDENTIALITY AND RECOMMENDATIONS FOR FOREIGN ARCHIVES AND LIBRARIES, 1936-1937 (Folder 2: 7)
- SERIES NO. 263. MINORITIES IN OTHER COUNTRIES
  - 1931-1938 (Folder 2: 8)
  - 1933 - Jewish minority in Germany (Folder 2: 9)
- SERIES NO. 272. EMIGRATION TRENDS, 1934-1939 (Folder 2: 10)
- SERIES NO. 276. CULTURAL AFFAIRS OF THE ÉMIGRÉS, 1932-1937 (Folder 2: 11)
- SERIES NO. 277. POLISH YOUTH STUDYING ABROAD, 1935 (Folder 2: 12)
- SERIES NO. 278. POLISH SETTLEMENTS ABROAD, 1933-1938 (Folder 2: 13)
- SERIES NO. 288. TRANSPORTATION OF EMIGRANTS, 1939
  - Group transports - Women (Folder 2: 14)
  - Individuals (Folder 2: 15)
- SERIES NO. 289. COMPETENCE OF EMIGRATION ADVISOR, 1934 (Folder 2: 16)
- SERIES NO. 298. POLISH SCHOOL SYSTEM ABROAD. ORGANIZATION AND PERSONNEL
  - 1924-1940 (Folder 2: 17)
  - 1933-1936 - Statistics on schools (Folder 2: 18)
  - 1938
    - General (Folder 2: 19)
    - List of teachers (Folder 2: 20)
  - 1938-1940 - School attendance (Folder 2: 21)
  - 1939 (Folder 2: 22)
  - 1940
    - General
      - January-February (Folder 2: 23)
      - March - Evacuation of children (Folder 2: 24)
      - March-May (Folder 2: 25)
    - List of teachers (Folder 2: 26)
- SERIES NO. 307. SOCIAL WELFARE FOR EMIGRANTS, 1937 (Folder 2: 27)
- SERIES NO. 308. WORK SEARCH AGENCIES FOR EMIGRANTS, 1940 (Folder 2: 28)
- SERIES NO. 310. ORGANIZATION OF ÉMIGRÉ MOVEMENTS, 1938-1939 (Folder 2: 29)
- SERIES NO. 311. POLISH YOUTH FROM ABROAD IN POLAND, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 3: 1)
- SERIES NO. 313. NATURALIZATION, 1933-1936 (Folder 3: 2)
- SERIES NO. 314. REEMIGRATION
  - 1932-1933 - Escorting (Folder 3: 3)
  - 1935 - Transport (Folder 3: 4)
  - 1935-1939 - Repatriation (Folder 3: 5)
- SERIES NO. 315. INFORMATION ON EMIGRATION MATTERS
  - General
    - 1927 (Folder 3: 6)
    - 1932 (Folder 3: 7)
    - 1932-1938 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Situation report
    - 1933 (Folder 3: 9)
    - 1934-1936 (Folder 3: 10)
- SERIES NO. 416. MEDALS AND DECORATIONS
  - 1931-1937 - Krzyz Zaslugi (Folder 3: 11)
  - 1934-1935 - Gwiazda Wolnosci (Folder 3: 12)
  - 1938
    - General
      - General (Folder 3: 13)
      - B-D (Folder 3: 14)
      - F-J (Folder 3: 15)
      - K (Folder 3: 16)
      - L-M (Folder 3: 17)
      - N-P (Folder 3: 18)
      - R-S (Folder 4: 1)
      - T-W (Folder 4: 2)
    - Lists (Folder 4: 3)
  - 1939 (Folder 4: 4)
- SERIES NO. 421. MARSHAL JOZEF PILSUDSKI, 1935-1938 (Folder 4: 5)
- SERIES NO. 424. DIPLOMATIC AND CONSULAR WORK. France, Consulates (Folder 4: 6)
- SERIES NO. 430. TAXATION, LIVING ACCOMMODATIONS, REGISTRATION WITH AUTHORITIES, DRAFT EXEMPTIONS, PERMISSION FOR PROPERTY PURCHASE
  - 1939 (Folder 4: 7)
  - 1940 - Tax exemption (Folder 4: 8)
- SERIES NO. 438. MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS ORGANIZATIONAL REGULATIONS
  - 1931-1936 (Folder 4: 9)
  - 1938-1939 (Folder 4: 10)
- SERIES NO. 449. NORMALIZATION OF PAPERWORK AND FORMS (Folder 4: 11)
- SERIES NO. 474. OFFICE CLERKS
  - General
    - 1936 (Folder 4: 12)
    - 1937 (Folder 4: 13)
    - 1938 (Folder 4: 14)
    - 1939 (Folder 4: 15)
    - 1940 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Consulate employees
    - Contracts (Folder 4: 17)
    - Files
      - General (Folder 4: 18)
      - Personal characteristics (Folder 4: 19)
    - Lists, 1932-1939 (Folder 4: 20)
- SERIES NO. 474/C. CONTRACT EMPLOYEES (Box 5)
  - General
    - A-D (Folder 5: 1)
    - F-K (Folder 5: 2)
    - K-L (Folder 5: 3)
    - M-O (Folder 5: 4)
    - P-R (Folder 5: 5)
    - S-U (Folder 5: 6)
    - W-Z (Folder 5: 7)
  - Individual files
    - Ablamowicz, Helena (Folder 5: 8)
    - Baworowski, Jan (Folder 5: 9)
    - Dobrowolski, Zygmunt (Folder 5: 10)
    - Domanski, Stefan (Folder 5: 11)
    - Friedrich, Artur (Folder 5: 12)
    - Gawrak, Zbigniew (Folder 5: 13)
    - Gocki, Franciszek (Folder 5: 14)
    - Gubrynowicz, Wladyslaw (Folder 5: 15)
    - Harwas, Jan (Folder 5: 16)
    - Jachimowicz, Jerzy (Folder 5: 17)
    - Kawalkowski, Aleksander
      - 1933-1936 (Folder 5: 18)
      - 1937 (Folder 5: 19)
      - 1938-1940 (Folder 5: 20)
    - Kielkowicz, Wladyslaw (Folder 6: 1)
    - Klejniak, Jozef (Folder 6: 2)
    - Korusiewicz, Leon (Folder 6: 3)
    - Kowalska, Wiktoria (Folder 6: 4)
    - Lesniewski, Michal
      - 1932-1937 (Folder 6: 5)
      - 1938 - Konsulat Generalny R.P. w Wiedniu (Folder 6: 6)
      - 1939 (Folder 6: 7)
    - Lisicki, Ryszard (Folder 6: 8)
    - Lopatto, Stanislaw (Folder 6: 9)
    - Makowski, Ludomir (Folder 6: 10)
    - Mercik, Stanislaw (Folder 6: 11)
    - Mielczarek, Mieczyslaw (Folder 6: 12)
    - Musielak, Stefan (Folder 6: 13)
    - Pilatowicz, Jerzy (Folder 6: 14)
    - Rozkosz, Jan (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Sas-Liskowacki, Wlodzimierz (Folder 7: 2)
    - Torchalski, Tomasz and Matuszewska, Franciszka (Folder 7: 3)
    - Wagnerowicz, Maria (Folder 7: 4)
    - Wanczycki, Jan (Folder 7: 5)
    - Wawak, Jan (Folder 7: 6)
    - Wentzel, Ludwik (Folder 7: 7)
    - Wisniewska, Wanda (Folder 7: 8)
    - Zamoyski, Zdzislaw (Folder 7: 9)
    - Zbik, Wladyslaw (Folder 7: 10)
    - Zochowna, Izabela (Folder 7: 11)
- SERIES NO. 439. CIRCULARS, 1938-1940 (Box-folder 8: 1)
- SERIES NO. 478. VARIOUS PERSONNEL MATTERS
  - 1931 (Folder 8: 2)
  - 1931-1936 (Folder 8: 3)
  - 1932 (Folder 8: 4)
  - 1933 (Folder 8: 5)
  - 1933-1940 (Folder 8: 6)
  - 1934 (Folder 8: 7)
  - 1935 (Folder 8: 8)
- SERIES NO. 481. SUMMER APPRENTICESHIP ABROAD OF POLISH STUDENTS, 1932-1939 (Folder 8: 9)
- SERIES NO. 501. DZIENNIK URZEDOWY MINISTERSTWA SPRAW ZAGRANICZNYCH, 1937-1938 (Folder 8: 10)
- SERIES NO. 509. VARIOUS PASSPORT ISSUES, 1933-1940 (Folder 8: 11)
- SERIES NO. 513. VARIOUS VISA ISSUES, 1939 (Folder 8: 12)
- SERIES NO. 516. COURIER MAIL. Transfer of money to Stockholm, 1939 (Folder 8: 13)
- SERIES NO. 527. MINISTRY'S HEADQUARTERS, 1938-1939 (Folder 8: 14)
- SERIES NO. 550. PROPAGANDA AND DISCRETIONARY FUNDS
  - 1933-1938 (Folder 8: 15)
  - 1939 - Education funds reports from Strasbourg Consulate (Folder 8: 16)
  - 1940
    - January (Folder 8: 17)
    - February (Folder 8: 18)
    - March (Folder 8: 19)
    - April (Folder 8: 20)
    - May (Folder 8: 21)
- SERIES NO. 563. CIRCULARS AND INSTRUCTIONS ON BUDGETARY AND ACCOUNTING ISSUES, 1934-1940 (Folder 8: 22)
- SERIES NO. 591. EMBASSY IN PARIS, FRANCE, 1938 (Folder 8: 23)
- SERIES NO. 593. CONSULATE GENERAL IN LILLE, FRANCE (Box 9)
  - General
    - 1936 (Folder 9: 1)
    - 1938 (Folder 9: 2)
    - 1939 (Folder 9: 3)
    - 1939-1940 (Folder 9: 4)
  - Loans for staff (Folder 9: 5)
- SERIES NO. 676. CONSULAR MEETINGS
  - 1935-1936 (Folder 9: 6)
  - 1938-1939 (Folder 9: 7)
- SERIES NO. 685/A. COMPLAINTS AT POLISH AGENCIES ABROAD
  - General, 1938-1939 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Travel bureau (Folder 9: 9)
- SERIES NO. 686. RATES AND CONSULAR SERVICES, 1935-1939 (Folder 9: 10)
- SERIES NO. 707/A. VITAL RECORDS, MARRIAGE. Civil cases and financial support of families in Poland (Folder 9: 11)
- SERIES NO. 715. FUNDAMENTAL ISSUES
  - 1930-1939 - Citizenship issues. (Folder 9: 12)
    Circulars
  - 1934-1939 (Folder 9: 13)
  - 1940. (Folder 9: 14)
    Includes passports of Julia Kic and Honorata Zelazo
- SERIES NO. 719. INVALIDATION OF POLISH CITIZENSHIP
  - 1939 (Folder 9: 15)
  - 1940 (Folder 9: 16)
- SERIES NO. 727. PASSPORT FUNDAMENTAL ISSUES
  - 1932-1937 - Passport's marking of suspected individuals (Folder 9: 17)
  - 1938-1940 (Folder 9: 18)
- SERIES NO. 728. PASSPORT REGULATIONS, 1934-1939 (Folder 9: 19)
- SERIES NO. 729. ISSUANCE AND EXTENSION OF PASSPORTS
  - 1933-1936 - Refusals (Folder 9: 20)
  - 1935-1939 (Folder 9: 21)
- SERIES NO. 730. INVALIDATION OF PASSPORTS, 1934-1936 (Folder 9: 22)
- SERIES NO. 733. VISA REGULATIONS, 1933-1938 (Folder 9: 23)
- SERIES NO. 735. POLISH VISAS, 1931-1939 (Folder 9: 24)
- SERIES NO. 741. EXPULSION OF POLISH CITIZENS, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 10: 1)
- SERIES NO. 745. MILITARY FUNDAMENTAL ISSUES, 1939 (Folder 10: 2)
- SERIES NO. 746. MILITARY REGULATIONS, 1935-1939. (Folder 10: 3)
  Recruitment of Poles into the Civil War in Spain. Includes lists of participants, 1938
- SERIES NO. 751. POLISH CITIZENS IN FOREIGN MILITARY SERVICE, 1938-1939. (Folder 10: 4)
  Includes list of volunteers in Spain
- SERIES NO. 755. POLISH ARMY ABROAD, 1939-1940. (Folder 10: 5)
  Recruitment of Polish youth, Possibility of
- SERIES NO. 758. SURVEILANCE, 1939
  - January (Folder 10: 6)
  - February-March (Folder 10: 7)
  - April. (Folder 10: 8)
    Includes lists of Gestapo agents
  - June - Individuals to be denied visas (Folder 10: 9)
  - July (Folder 10: 10)
- SERIES NO. 761/D. INFORMATION RELATED TO NATIONAL SECURITY, COMMUNISTS
  - General
    - 1932 (Folder 10: 11)
    - 1933 (Folder 10: 12)
    - 1934 (Folder 10: 13)
    - 1935 (Folder 10: 14)
    - 1936
      - General (Folder 10: 15)
      - Clippings (Folder 10: 16)
    - 1937-1938 - Prokopow, Michal (Folder 10: 17)
    - 1937-1939 (Folder 10: 18)
  - Communist fliers from 1930s (Folder 10: 19)
  - Sympathizers of Dziennik Ludowy file (Folder 10: 20)
- SERIES NO. 761/G. UKRAINIAN MOVEMENT
  - 1932-1939 (Folder 10: 21)
  - 1939 (Folder 10: 22)
- SERIES NO. 761/I. INFORMATION RELATED TO NATIONAL SECURITY, OTHER ORGANIZATIONS AND INDIVIDUALS (Box 11)
  - 1932-1934 (Folder 11: 1)
  - 1935-1939 (Folder 11: 2)
- SERIES NO. 764. INTERNAL POLITICAL SITUATION IN POLAND, 1937-1938 (Folder 11: 3)
- SERIES NO. 765. INVESTIGATIONS AND UNPROCESSED MATERIAL RELATED TO NATIONAL SECURITY
  - 1930-1938 (Folder 11: 4)
  - 1939 (Folder 11: 5)
  - 1940 (Folder 11: 6)
- SERIES NO. 773. INFORMATION ON TRADE, 1931-1938 (Folder 11: 7)
- SERIES NO. 775. TAXATION. Taxes and contributions for the war purposes, 1939-1940 (Folder 11: 8)
- SERIES NO. 784. PENSIONS AND OTHER SERVICES, 1936-1937 (Folder 11: 9)
- SERIES NO. 788. LOANS AND RELIEF, 1936-1938 (Folder 11: 10)
- SERIES NO. 789/A. HEALTH CARE COSTS OF POLISH CITIZENS ABROAD, 1934 (Folder 11: 11)
- SERIES NO. 791. DONATIONS AND COLLECTIONS FOR VARIOUS CAUSES
  - 1934-1938 (Folder 11: 12)
  - 1936-1939 - Fundusz Obrony Narodowej (Folder 11: 13)
- SERIES NO. 805. DEPOSITS, 1935 (Folder 11: 14)
- SERIES NO. 817. CONSTITUTION OF THE REPUBLIC OF POLAND, 1934 (Folder 11: 15)
- SERIES NO. 851/E. MINORITIES IN POLAND AND AFFAIRS RELATED TO THEM OUTSIDE OF POLAND, 1937
  - General. Circulars (Folder 11: 16)
  - Glowne Organizacje Zydowskie Polityczne i Spoleczne
    - Chart (Folder 11: 17)
    - Mimeographed copy (Folder 11: 18)
  - Problem Emigracji Zydowskiej
    - Mimeographed copy
      - Part I (Folder 11: 19)
      - Part II (Folder 11: 20)
      - Part III (Folder 11: 21)
    - Printed copy. (Folder 11: 22)
      Includes maps